<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE bookinfo PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<bookinfo>
  <othercredit role="proofreader">
    <firstname>Sarah</firstname>

    <surname>Schneider</surname>
  </othercredit>

  <othercredit role="interiordesigner">
    <firstname>David</firstname>

    <surname>Futato</surname>
  </othercredit>

  <othercredit role="illustrator">
    <firstname>Robert</firstname>

    <surname>Romano</surname>
  </othercredit>

  <!-- All rights reserved. -->

  <publisher>
    <publishername>O’Reilly Media, Inc.</publishername>

    <address format="linespecific">
      <street>1005 Gravenstein Highway North</street>
      <city>Sebastopol</city>
      <state>CA</state>
      <postcode>95472</postcode>
    </address>
  </publisher>

  <legalnotice role="printlocation">
    <para>Printed in the United States of America.</para>
  </legalnotice>

  <legalnotice role="printer">
    <para>[M]</para>
  </legalnotice>

  <legalnotice role="use">
    <para>O’Reilly books may be purchased for educational, business, or sales
    promotional use. Online editions are also available for most titles
    (<ulink role="orm:hideurl:ital"
    url="http://my.safaribooksonline.com/?portal=oreilly">http://my.safaribooksonline.com</ulink>).
    For more information, contact our corporate/institutional sales
    department: 800-998-9938 or <email>corporate@oreilly.com</email>.</para>
  </legalnotice>

  <legalnotice role="trademarks">
    <para>O’Reilly and the O’Reilly logo are registered trademarks of O’Reilly
    Media, Inc. <citetitle>Programming Scala</citetitle>, the image of a
    Malayan tapir, and related trade dress are trademarks of O’Reilly Media,
    Inc.</para>

    <para>Many of the designations used by manufacturers and sellers to
    distinguish their products are claimed as trademarks. Where those
    designations appear in this book, and O’Reilly Media, Inc. was aware of a
    trademark claim, the designations have been printed in caps or initial
    caps.</para>
  </legalnotice>

  <legalnotice role="damages">
    <para>While every precaution has been taken in the preparation of this
    book, the publisher and authors assume no responsibility for errors or
    omissions, or for damages resulting from the use of the information
    contained herein. This work has been released under the <ulink
    url="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">Creative Commons
    Attribution-Noncommercial license</ulink>.</para>
  </legalnotice>

  <isbn>9780596155957</isbn>

  <edition>1</edition>

  <author>
    <firstname>Dean</firstname>

    <surname>Wampler</surname>

    <authorblurb>
      <para><emphasis role="strong">Dean Wampler</emphasis> is a consultant,
      trainer, and mentor with Object Mentor, Inc. He specializes in Scala,
      Java, and Ruby. He works with clients on application design strategies
      that combine object-oriented programming, functional programming, and
      aspect-oriented programming. He also consults on Agile methods, such as
      Lean and XP. Dean is a frequent speaker at industry and academic
      conferences on these topics. He has a Ph.D. in physics from the
      University of Washington.</para>
    </authorblurb>
  </author>

  <author>
    <firstname>Alex</firstname>

    <surname>Payne</surname>

    <authorblurb>
      <para><emphasis role="strong">Alex Payne</emphasis> currently works for
      Twitter, Inc., a communications service that allows users to send short
      one-to-many messages via a variety of media. His title at Twitter is API
      Lead; his daily work is growing and supporting a collection of services
      on which other developers can build. Alex has been working at Twitter
      since the beginning of 2007, several months before the service began to
      grow in popularity. Before working at Twitter, Alex worked in
      information security, helped build web applications for political
      campaigns, non-profits, and more. In his free time, Alex studies the
      history, present use, and evolution of programming languages, as well as
      minimalist art and design. Alex lives and works in San Francisco, where
      he engages in an endless search for the perfect cocktail and cup of
      coffee.</para>
    </authorblurb>
  </author>

  <editor>
    <firstname>Mike</firstname>

    <surname>Loukides</surname>
  </editor>

  <copyright>
    <year>2009</year>

    <holder>Dean Wampler and Alex Payne</holder>
  </copyright>

  <editor role="production">
    <firstname>Sarah</firstname>

    <surname>Schneider</surname>
  </editor>

  <othercredit role="indexer">
    <firstname>Ellen</firstname>

    <surname>Troutman Zaig</surname>
  </othercredit>

  <othercredit role="coverdesigner">
    <firstname>Karen</firstname>

    <surname>Montgomery</surname>
  </othercredit>

  <printhistory>
    <formalpara>
      <title>First Edition</title>

      <para>September, 2009</para>
    </formalpara>
  </printhistory>
</bookinfo>