<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE preface PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<preface id="Preface">
  <title>Preface</title>

  <para><citetitle>Programming Scala</citetitle> introduces an exciting new
  language that offers all the benefits of a modern object model, functional
  programming, and an advanced type system. Packed with code examples, this
  comprehensive book teaches you how to be productive with Scala quickly, and
  explains what makes this language ideal for today’s highly scalable,
  component-based applications that support concurrency and distribution.
  You’ll also learn the advantages that Scala offers as a language for the
  Java Virtual Machine.</para>

  <para>Learn more at <ulink role="orm:hideurl:ital"
  url="http://programmingscala.com">programmingscala.com</ulink> or at the
  book’s <ulink url="http://oreilly.com/catalog/9780596155957/">catalog
  page</ulink>.</para>

  <sect1 id="_conventions_used_in_this_book">
    <title>Conventions Used in This Book</title>

    <para id="para_the_following_typographical_co">The following typographical
    conventions are used in this book:</para>

    <variablelist id="para_book_conventions">
      <varlistentry id="varlistentry-italic">
        <term><emphasis>Italic</emphasis></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Indicates new terms, URLs, email addresses, file names, and
          file extensions. Many italicized terms are defined in the <xref
          linkend="Glossary" />.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry id="varlistentry-constant-width">
        <term><literal>Constant width</literal></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Used for program listings, as well as within paragraphs to
          refer to program elements such as variable or function names,
          databases, data types, environment variables, statements, and
          keywords.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry id="varlistentry-constant-width-bold">
        <term><userinput>Constant width bold</userinput></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Shows commands or other text that should be typed literally by
          the user.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry id="varlistentry-constant-width-italic">
        <term><replaceable>Constant width italic</replaceable></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Shows text that should be replaced with user-supplied values
          or by values determined by context.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <tip id="para_tip_this_icon_signifies_a_tip">
      <para>This icon signifies a tip, suggestion, or general note.</para>
    </tip>

    <caution id="para_caution_this_icon_indicates_a">
      <para>This icon indicates a warning or caution.</para>
    </caution>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="UsingCodeExamples">
    <title>Using Code Examples</title>

    <para id="para_this_book_is_here_to_help_you_">This book is here to help
    you get your job done. In general, you may use the code in this book in
    your programs and documentation. You do not need to contact us for
    permission unless you’re reproducing a significant portion of the code.
    For example, writing a program that uses several chunks of code from this
    book does not require permission. Selling or distributing a CD-ROM of
    examples from O’Reilly books does require permission. Answering a question
    by citing this book and quoting example code does not require permission.
    Incorporating a significant amount of example code from this book into
    your product’s documentation does require permission.</para>

    <para id="para_we_appreciate_but_do_not_requ">We appreciate, but do not
    require, attribution. An attribution usually includes the title, author,
    publisher, and ISBN. For example: “<emphasis>Programming Scala</emphasis>
    by Dean Wampler and Alex Payne. Copyright 2009 Dean Wampler and Alex
    Payne, 978-0-596-15595-7.”</para>

    <para id="para_if_you_feel_your_use_of_code_e">If you feel your use of
    code examples falls outside fair use or the permission given above, feel
    free to contact us at <email>permissions@oreilly.com</email>.</para>

    <sect2 id="GettingCodeExamples">
      <title>Getting the Code Examples</title>

      <para id="para_you_can_download_the_code_exam">You can download the code
      examples from TODO. Unzip the files to a convenient location. See the
      <filename>README.txt</filename> file in the distribution for
      instructions on building and using the examples.</para>

      <para id="para_file_name_conventions">Some of the example files can be
      run as scripts using the <userinput>scala</userinput> command. Others
      must be compiled into class files. Some files contain deliberate errors
      and won’t compile. We have adopted a file naming convention to indicate
      each of these cases, although as you learn Scala it should become
      obvious from the contents of the files, in most cases.</para>

      <variablelist id="para_script_file_convention">
        <varlistentry id="varlistentry-script-scala">
          <term><filename>*-script.scala</filename></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Files that end in <filename>-script.scala</filename> can be
            run on a command line using <userinput>scala</userinput>, e.g.,
            <userinput>scala foo-script.scala</userinput>. You can also start
            <userinput>scala</userinput> in the interpreter mode (when you
            don’t specify a script file) and load any script file in the
            interpreter using the <literal>:load filename</literal>
            command.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry id="varlistentry-wont-compile-scala">
          <term><filename>*-wont-compile.scala</filename></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Files that end in <filename>-wont-compile.scala</filename>
            contain deliberate errors that will cause them to fail to compile.
            We use this naming convention, along with one or more embedded
            comments about the errors, so it will be clear that they are
            invalid. Also, these files are skipped by the build process for
            the examples.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry id="varlistentry-sake-scala">
          <term><filename>sake.scala</filename></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Files named <filename>sake.scala</filename> are used by our
            build tool, called <userinput>sake</userinput>. The
            <filename>README.txt</filename> file describes this tool.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry id="varlistentry-scala">
          <term><filename>*.scala</filename></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>All other Scala files must be compiled using
            <userinput>scalac</userinput>. In the distribution, they are used
            either by other compiled or script files, such as tests, not all
            of which are listed in the book.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="para_other_file_convention">
    <title>Safari® Books Online</title>

    <note id="para_note_when_you_see_a_safari_">
      <para>When you see a Safari® Books Online icon on the cover of your
      favorite technology book, that means the book is available online
      through the O’Reilly Network Safari Bookshelf.</para>
    </note>

    <para id="para_safari_offers_a_solution_that_">Safari offers a solution
    that’s better than e-books. It’s a virtual library that lets you easily
    search thousands of top tech books, cut and paste code samples, download
    chapters, and find quick answers when you need the most accurate, current
    information. Try it for free at <ulink role="orm:hideurl:ital"
    url="http://my.safaribooksonline.com/?portal=oreilly">http://my.safaribooksonline.com</ulink>.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="_how_to_contact_us">
    <title>How to Contact Us</title>

    <para id="para_please_address_comments_and_qu">Please address comments and
    questions concerning this book to the publisher:</para>

    <simplelist type="vert">
      <member>O’Reilly Media, Inc.</member>

      <member>1005 Gravenstein Highway North</member>

      <member>Sebastopol, CA 95472</member>

      <member>800-998-9938 (in the United States or Canada)</member>

      <member>707-829-0515 (international or local)</member>

      <member>707-829-0104 (fax)</member>
    </simplelist>

    <para id="para_we_have_a_web_page_for_this_bo">We have a web page for this
    book, where we list errata, examples, and any additional information. You
    can access this page at:</para>

    <simplelist type="vert">
      <member><ulink
      url="http://oreilly.com/catalog/9780596155957/"></ulink></member>
    </simplelist>

    <para id="para_to_comment_or_ask_technical_qu">To comment or ask technical
    questions about this book, send email to:</para>

    <simplelist type="vert">
      <member><email>bookquestions@oreilly.com</email></member>
    </simplelist>

    <para id="para_for_more_information_about_our">For more information about
    our books, conferences, Resource Centers, and the <phrase
    role="keep-together">O’Reilly</phrase> Network, see our website at:</para>

    <simplelist type="vert">
      <member><ulink url="http://oreilly.com"></ulink></member>
    </simplelist>
  </sect1>
</preface>