<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE preface PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<preface id="foreword" role="foreword">
  <prefaceinfo>
    <author>
      <firstname>Fred</firstname>

      <surname>Stringer</surname>

      <affiliation>
        <jobtitle></jobtitle>
      </affiliation>
    </author>

    <date>June 1, 2009</date>
  </prefaceinfo>

  <title>Foreword</title>

  <para>The exchange of information via digital communication networks has
  never been more critical and important than it is today. A few years ago we
  labeled specific traffic, separate circuits, or dedicated networks as being
  <emphasis>mission critical</emphasis>. Today, it is typical for the
  communications that support our lives, such as the Supervisory Control And
  Data Acquisition (SCADA) communications for our drinking water supplies, to
  be labeled mission critical—critical not just to a corporation’s business
  but to the global economy. The applications for communication networks
  continue to expand, adding more critical uses such as remote surgical
  consultation, distance health care, electrical power generation command and
  control, industrial support systems, and banking. The list is nearly
  endless, and as soon as it appears, it is out-of-date. The expectation is
  that communication networks will always be ready and able to exchange
  information.</para>

  <para>The network engineer has the task of designing a network and service
  that meets the defined requirements, typically a long list of items
  balancing technical, operational, and financial characteristics. It might
  include a list of IT applications and services for which the engineer has to
  determine the appropriate transmission tolerances (for example delay,
  jitter, packet loss, or bit error rate). The requirements list might also
  have a business priority for the various applications, or the requirements
  might be more vague and left to the engineer’s discretion. Regardless if it
  is defined, when a company invests money in a network it has a justified
  expectation that that network will be highly available—and the most likely
  expectation is that it will be available all the time, or 100% availability.
  Engineers and statisticians will immediately see the error in that
  expectation. Most network users and customers see no flaws in the 100%
  expectation. The term <emphasis>high availability</emphasis> in
  communication networks typically means that the network is ready to provide
  the service required by the user 99.999% of the time. That requirement
  allows for about five minutes of outage time per year. Of course, most users
  expect that outage will not occur when they are using the network
  services.</para>

  <para>To design a high availability network and service, the designer must
  consider a rather long list of factors, starting with the failure rate of
  the network elements (NEs) such as routers, switches, and gateways. This
  includes all the available component redundancies and optional capabilities,
  the failure rate of the circuits connecting the NEs, the amount of
  interconnect between the NE (a.k.a. the network topology), the
  routing/switching architectures, the alternate path capabilities, alternate
  routing and switching features, and on and on. The complete list is
  potentially an entire chapter of a book, even without a discussion of how
  the variables perform and interact.</para>

  <para>Large organizations often have the resources to divide the network
  design tasks across groups of specialists. The engineers responsible for
  meeting the availability objective are often well versed in failure
  analysis, mathematics, and statistics. A quick web search shows that there
  are a number of texts available on the subject for the mathematically
  inclined. Operating systems like JUNOS are an area of study unto themselves,
  and there is certainly no shortage of detailed analysis on the various
  architectures, all documented in books.</para>

  <para>Most networks operate without a large staff of specialists. The
  engineers don’t have time to do a deep-dive study of OS architectures,
  system architectures, or a detailed analysis of each subassembly of a
  system. They need a resource with just enough descriptive detail on the
  features and functions of the equipment and the network features it
  provides. They need useful tools that include real examples of user commands
  and system messages—and having troubleshooting guidance in the same place is
  a real advantage. They need a pragmatic perspective and a few tools for
  making comparative analysis, which are as useful for designing a greenfield
  network as they are for augmenting part of the network or improving the
  availability performance of an existing network.</para>

  <para>And that is exactly what Orin Blomberg, James Sonderegger, Senad
  Palislamovic, and Kieran Milne accomplish in <citetitle>JUNOS High
  Availability</citetitle>. You won’t find a theoretical study of the Juniper
  operating system, detailed analysis of the software architecture, failure
  mode effects analysis, a Markov model of the probable failure modes and
  recovery performance, or Weibull analysis. The goal of the text is not to
  make you a reliability expert. The goal is to help you create, implement,
  and maintain an effective network design with Juniper Networks devices
  running JUNOS software. The goal is help you create continuous systems that
  are up 99.999% of the time.</para>
</preface>